Guide to the Donald T. Carlson Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Donald T. Carlson papers
1952-1995
SC0539
Carlson, Donald T.
2.75 Linear feet
These papers contain correspondence files and subject files. The correspondence, with Stanford officials, alumni, and colleagues at other colleges, pertains to alumni relations, donor relations, campus events making national news, and other aspects of his public relations work; correspondents include Stanford president J. E. Wallace Sterling, Fred Glover, Lyle Nelson, Elinor V. Cogswell, Stanford trustee Richard E. Guggenhime, and Robert E. Kennedy of Cal-Poly. There is also some correspondence with friends and family. The subject files contain correspondence, clippings, reports, memoranda, text for talks, articles, photographs, and other items pertaining to campus events, student publications, the history of university relations at Stanford, and fellow administrative staff, especially their retirement parties for which Carlson often composed song parodies. Of note are files on the guest professorship for Angela Davis in 1976, sponsored by the Associated Students of Stanford University; the 1962 Stanford Summer Institute in Germany; the career of J. E. Wallace Sterling; a report on the University of Sonora (Mexico) by Santiago Cota de la Torre, 1971; and THE ORAL HISTORY OF DAVID S. JACOBSON, which includes the 1978 SOHP transcript, a supplement by Jacobson done in 1985, and additional materials prepared by his family.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Donald Carlson, 1997.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Carlson earned his A.B. in journalism and social sciences at Stanford in 1947. He was executive secretary of college relations at Oregon State College, as well as instructor in journalism, before returning to Stanford in 1951 as assistant director of information. In 1954 he was appointed assistant to the president in charge of the University's Southern California office. After 5 years in Southern California he returned to the main campus, where he continued as assistant to the president. In 1962 he was appointed Associate Director of University Relations, and Director in 1978. He retired in 1986.
Description of the Collection
These papers contain correspondence files and subject files. The correspondence, with Stanford officials, alumni, and colleagues at other colleges, pertains to alumni relations, donor relations, campus events making national news, and other aspects of his public relations work; correspondents include Stanford president J. E. Wallace Sterling, Fred Glover, Lyle Nelson, Elinor V. Cogswell, Stanford trustee Richard E. Guggenhime, and Robert E. Kennedy of Cal-Poly. There is also some correspondence with friends and family. The subject files contain correspondence, clippings, reports, memoranda, text for talks, articles, photographs, and other items pertaining to campus events, student publications, the history of university relations at Stanford, and fellow administrative staff, especially their retirement parties for which Carlson often composed song parodies. Of note are files on the guest professorship for Angela Davis in 1976, sponsored by the Associated Students of Stanford University; the 1962 Stanford Summer Institute in Germany; the career of J. E. Wallace Sterling; a report on the University of Sonora (Mexico) by Santiago Cota de la Torre, 1971; and THE ORAL HISTORY OF DAVID S. JACOBSON, which includes the 1978 SOHP transcript, a supplement by Jacobson done in 1985, and additional materials prepared by his family.
Access Terms
Carlson, Donald T.; Cogswell, Elinor.; Davis, Angela Y., (Angela Yvonne), 1944-; Glover, Frederic O.; Jacobson, David S.; Kennedy, Robert Edwin.; Munford, James Kenneth.; Nelson, Lyle M.; Sterling, J. E. Wallace, (John Ewart Wallace), 1906-1985; Educational fund raising.; Public relations--Universities and colleges.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  The following file has been pulled and is restricted until September 2009:
  Beyers, Robert and Stanford News Service, 1989-90 [filed with other restricted folders from SC collections in GW 403].
  Items removed from collection:
  The Teaching of Religion at Stanford, ca. 1953.
  SLAC, brochure prepared in honor of H. E. Mr. Georges Pompidou on his visit to SLAC, Feb. 27, 1970.
  Friedman, Milton. Why Government is the Problem. Hoover Institution. Essays in Public Policy, 1993.
  SLAC News, Vol. 1, No. 1, Feb. 26, 1970. [Pompidou visit].
  Stanford University. Administrative Manual. Sixth Edition, 1958.
  Techniques, Vol. 4, No. 1, Jan/Feb. 1969 [pub of American College Public Relations Association]
  Chaparral. Big Game Issue, November 1950.
  Sandstone and Tile, Vol. 9, No. 4, Summer 1985 [Sterling article].
  Campus Report, issues of April 24, 1974, July 3, 1985, and April 16, 1986.
  Stanford Observer, July 1985.
  - Correspondence, 1952-59 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1962-63 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1964-66 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1967 Jan. – June (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1967 July – Sept. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1967 Oct. – Dec. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1968 Jan. – April (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1968 May – Oct. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1968 Nov. – Dec. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1969 Jan. – May (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1969 June – Nov. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1972-73 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1979 Jan. – April (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1979 June – Dec. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1983-84 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1985 Jan. – May (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1985 June – Dec. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1986-95 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: undated note from Wallace Stegner (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - ACPRA meeting, Jan. 29, 1970 (text of remarks by Carlson and others) (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - ACPRA meeting, 1974 (text of remarks by Carlson) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Allen, Pete – party for, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - ASSU guest professorship for Angela Davis, April 1976 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - ASSU guest professorship for Angela Davis, April 1976 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Bing, Peter, Remarks to University Fellows, June 4, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Biographical material on Carlson (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Bliven, Bruce (text of talk on Bliven by Carlson) (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Cal Poly, 1974-80 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Campaign for Stanford – draft plan for public relations, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Carlson, "A New Look at Old Ways," based on comments to class representations at the Annual Fund Conference, Sept. 16, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Carlson, "A Sketch of the University Relations Operations under the Vice President for Public Affairs," June 6, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Chaparral, correspondence regarding, 1969-81 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Dormitories at other institutions, 1952-53 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Fagan, Elmer – hoax newspaper story, 1961, and obituary, ca. 1971 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Fredlund family history (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Glover, Fred – oral history transcript (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Humphrey, Vice President Hubert – visit of, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Jacobson, David – oral history transcript (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Kennedy, Donald, inauguration – historical text by Carlson, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - "Liberated documents" Published by the Underground Press, Stanford, May 1969 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Middleton, Tex – tribute to by D. Jacobson, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous clippings (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Newell, Thomas – Carlson's remarks at farewell dinner, 1977, and obituary, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Newman, Frank – party for (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Notes for a talk to high school newspaper staff on public relations (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Oregon State University (brochures and publications) Panel for Newcomers [to Stanford], Nov. 14, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Photographs (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Pitzer, Kenneth – dinner in honor of, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Retirement party for Carlson, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Rose Bowl, 1971-72, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Song parodies (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Stanford Associates, 50th Anniversary, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Stanford Associates, reports and miscellany (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Stanford Daily - correspondence, clippings, 1971-74; includes "A Report on the use of a Search Warrant Against the Stanford Daily," by Dick Fogel (Sigma Delta Chi) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Stanford memorabilia (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Stanford Summer Institute, Germany, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Stanford Summer Institute, Germany, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Stanford University, general information (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Sterling, J. E. Wallace – Syntex dedication, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Sterling, J. E. Wallace – office fire, July 5, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Sterling, J. E. Wallace – Faculty club show, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Sterling, J. E. Wallace – 25th Anniversary celebration, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Sterling, J. E. Wallace – proposed article for Stanford Magazine, 1977 [not published] (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Sterling, J. E. Wallace – biographical articles (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Sterling, J. E. Wallace – session on Wally 1985 (transcripts) (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Sterling, J. E. Wallace – session on Wally 1985 (transcripts) (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Sterling, J. E. Wallace – memorial booklet, possible text (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Taylor, Chuck – biographical material (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Travel and expense records (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Tulane University School of Medicine, report on public relations by Carlson, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - University of Sonora: Some Problems, Some Solutions, by Santiago Cota de la Torre, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - University relations, Carlson's history at Stanford 1961-85 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - University relations at Stanford, miscellaneous items (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - University Relations Report to the Long-Range Planning Committee, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Vickers, Judge Joe, oral history transcript and related correspondence, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Watkins, James – tribute to, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Weigle, Clifford, obituary 1981 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Winbigler, H. Donald, "Leland Stanford Jr., a Centennial Lecture" adapted for Campus Report by Don Carlson, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - "Words Worth a Second Thought," miscellaneous text (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Address book (M-Z) (Box 6)
  - Slides (9) pertaining to Stanford (includes Sterling and Kennedy in academic dress, Stanford Indian head 1975, Fred Glover, copy of image of the first library, Stanford Band at football game 1975) (Box 6)
  - Slides from a trip? (winter scenes in the west) (Box 6)
  - "background tape for the "Lyman Years"; cassette box is labeled Songs by Harry Dec. 1992 / Christmas morning with Harry Dec. 1991), May, 1980; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 6)
  - Copy of "A Session on Wally" 1985 (Box 6)
  - Bound copy of The Oral History of David S. Jacobson, which includes the 1978 SOHP transcript, a supplement by Jacobson done in 1985, and additional materials prepared by his family (photographs and Jacobson's columns from alumni publications) (Box 6)